Leah: So, what is the Waterfall approach?
Chris: Waterfall project management
emphasises a linear approach from the
beginning to the end of a project.
It flows like a waterfall through all
phases of a project with each phase
wrapping up before the next phase begins.
It is often used by engineers and
is front loaded relying on careful
planning, detailed documentation,
and consecutive execution.
It follows a chronological
process and works on fixed dates,
requirements, and outcomes.
Leah: In Waterfall Project
Management there are typically four
main roles across the team Let’s
have a look at what these are.
The Project Manager, who is the
Leader of the team and responsible
for quality and deadlines.
They are responsible for managing
the project and subdividing the
tasks to the other team members.
Chris: A Business Analyst, whose role
involves research and helping the team
to understand the requirements to make
the product competitive in the market.
Developers who build the product
and create and write the code.
Testers who test the final
product making sure it functions
correctly and there are no bugs.
Leah: There are three main
principles with the Waterfall model
Chris: Low customer involvement is
connected to strong documentation
as this is one of the reasons that
they don’t need to be involved
in every stage of the project.
For most projects there are only two
meetings with the client, initially
before the project starts which is where
the learning and documentation of the
client’s requirements takes place, and
then a second meeting which is after the
final product is ready to be deployed.
Leah: Strong documentation is created
at every stage of the project.
This includes initial documents created
in agreement with the customer which
would include the requirements of the
client for the final software product.
Chris: Sequential structure is the
main principle of the Waterfall model,
and most projects have 5 to 7 stages.
Leah: Let’s have a look at
these stages in more detail.
Stage 1.
Analysis and requirements
Chris: This is the stage where
all the customer requirements are
gathered by the team in the form of
a document which would include costs,
assumptions, risks, dependencies,
measurements, and a timeline.
This meeting would be very thorough to
ensure that there wouldn’t be a need
for further communication with the
client until the end of the project.
Leah: Stage 2.
Design
This is the stage where the
team would design a technical
solution for the project.
It would include logical and
physical design and would involve
the team and the Project Manager.
Chris: Stage 3.
Implementation
the team would start to create the
actual code based on the requirements
and specification that has been
identified in the previous stages.
Leah: Stage 4.
Testing and verification
Testing is done at this stage by
the QA team to make sure that there
are no errors and that all the
requirements have been completed.
User testing may also
be done at this stage.
Chris: Stage 5.
Deployment and release
Once the client is happy with the
product and it has been reviewed and
signed off, the product can be deployed.
Leah: Stage 6.
Maintenance
This stage would be to ensure if
there are any errors or bugs, updates,
and or new features that are needed
once the product has been released.